Guide to the Travelers in the Middle East collection of travel guides, narratives and images, circa 1852-2004 MS 585
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Travelers in the Middle East collection of travel guides, narratives and images
1852-2004
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Sanders, Paula
MS 585
4 Linear Feet 6 boxes
This collection consists of the physical materials that are represented digitally in the Travelers in the Middle East Archive (TIMEA), a collection created to make possible the study of Western interactions with the Middle East, particularly travel to Egypt in the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. The materials are of diverse types: images in the forms of post cards, photographs, and stereograph films; articles, pamphlets, and travel guidebooks; maps, and souvenirs.
Biographical / Historical
The Travelers in the Middle East Archive (TIMEA) is an archive of materials that reflect Western interactions with the Middle East, particularly Egypt, during the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. This collection is composed of physical items in the archive apart from illustrations and photographs in books that are referenced in the related digital project, which is online at timea.rice.edu. These physical items are a variety of formats, including travel guides, museum catalogs, travel narratives; post cards and stereographic views of monuments, street scenes, people, and events; maps; pamphlets; souvenir programs; and souvenir objects.
The collection was assembled by Dr. Paula Sanders, Professor of History at Rice University. Many of the items were acquired over the period of time she prepared to write Creating Medieval Cairo: Empire, religion, and architectural preservation in nineteenth-century Egypt (American University in Cairo Press, 2008). Her gathering of items began when she was Scholar in Residence at the American Research Center in Egypt in 1995-96.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of the physical materials that are represented digitally in the Travelers in the Middle East Archive (TIMEA), a collection created to make possible the study of Western interactions with the Middle East, particularly travel to Egypt in the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. The materials are of diverse types: images in the forms of post cards, photographs, and stereograph films; articles, pamphlets, and travel guidebooks; maps, and souvenirs.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Dr. Paula Sanders, January 2016.
Related Materials
Published books donated as part of this collection have been cataloged separately in the Woodson's rare book collection, stored off-site at the Library Service Center. These books can be identified by having the following note: "Donated by Paula Sanders. This text is part of the Travelers in the Middle East Archive (TIMEA), funded by the Institute of Museum and Library Services (IMLS), and the Computer and Information Technology Institute (CITi), Rice University."
See also: Sanders, Paula. Creating Medieval Cairo: Empire, religion, and architectural preservation in nineteenth-century Egypt.
Related Materials
This collection of physical materials is to some some degree represented online by the Travelers in the Middle East project (TIMEA) located at http://timea.rice.edu/. The Travelers in the Middle East Archive (TIMEA) is a digital archive that focuses on Western interactions with the Middle East, particularly travels to Egypt during the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. TIMEA offers electronic texts such as travel guides, museum catalogs, and travel narratives, photographic and hand-drawn images of Egypt, and historical maps of Egypt and Cyprus. In addition, TIMEA provides educational modules that set the materials in context and explore how to conduct historical research.
Index Terms
Subjects
Travelers' writings; Travellers and explorers; Voyages and travels; Social life and customs
Document Types
Maps; photographs
Places
Asian Americans
- Series I: Photographs, 1880s and undated
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of 144 items in addition to a 36-page leather-bound album with pages filled with small black and white prints. Of these there is random labeling, e.g. "Heliopolis," "on the Nile," "modern Cairo" (with automobile resembling 1930's design). 41 of the loose photographs are approximately 5"x7" and contain images of buildings, architectural details, statues, and a few people. 70 are approximately 4"x6", also images of buildings, decorative elements, and people. There are 4 photocards of items at the Musée de Boulaq. From a set labeled "20 Cairo Snaps," there are 6 labeled 2"x3"black and white photos. Finally, there are 23 of a 25-photocard set titled Monuments Choisés de Musée de Boulaq" with Texte Explicatif dated 1881.
  - Scrapbook of street scenes and people, Heliopolis, Egypt (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cairo snapshots (professional printed with numbers and place names on the reverse, in a red envelope identifying "Publ. A. Copyr, by Lehnart & Landrock, Succs. Series 302" - 6 b/w images, 2" x 3.5" (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Monuments Choisis du Musee de Boulaq (Egypt), Collection de 25 photographies avec texts explicatif par Emile Brugsch, Conservateur Adj. du Musee (23 prints included here, plus descriptive text pamphlet), 1881 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photo cards from Musee de Boulaq (Egypt), 4 prints mounted on yellow cards, by E. Edwards (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Snapshots of street scenes, building details and people, some identified, various sizes 5x7" and smaller (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Color postcards / advertisements (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Stereographs, 1890s
  In addition to 118 stereographs of Egyptian subjects and scenes, there are 71 of other locations, primarily European and American.
  - Egypt views, labeled with numbers EgyV7_001 - EgyV7_040, missing #19 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Egypt views, labeled with numbers EgyV7_0041 - EgyV7_0114 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Numbered set of views by T. W. Ingersoll, of street scenes, building views, interiors, landscapes in the US, Mexico, Europe, Algiers, Egypt, and elsewhere, all printed with green card background and a description on the reverse (71 items), 1890s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cairo as represented in American world fairs (4 views), and views of Cairo (2), 1893-1894 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Stereo viewer tool (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series III: Postcards, 1900-2004
  This series contains 315 postcards of Egyptian scenes and subjects. 157 are loose, 152 are in labeled sets ranging in size from 4 to 24, and 6 are larger than standard size.
  - Postcards grouped at EgyV5, generally of Cairo scenes (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Postcards grouped as EgyV6, generally Heliopolis (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Loose postcards, ca. 1900-2004 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Postcard sets, Egypt (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Printed travel guidebooks and souvenir programs, 1883-1958
  There are 8 items in this series, the longest of which is an undated 9-3/16"x5-13/16" booklet of black and white photographs titled Souvenir of Cairo. Another of the items is a photograph-illustrataed engagement book style calendar titled Egypt 1958.
  - Souvenir of Cairo booklet, published by the Cairo Postcard Trust, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Red booklet of Cairo and Egypt views, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Egypt calendar spiral bound booklet, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "Street in Cairo: World's Columbian Exposition," booklet, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - A Brief Guide to Al-Haram Al-Sharif Jerusalem, published by the Supreme Moslem Council, 1924 and 1935 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - E. Tourjee's Educational Excursions to Europe, travel brochure, Boston, Mass., 1883 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series V: Souvenirs and ephemera, 1852-1986
  There are 20 items in this series. 8 are short publications. 5 objects include a bronze commemorative medal; a pair of 45-rpm vinyl discs with Sono Cairo and Arabic writing on the jacket; 2 3"x5" fabric leaves, one with the Egyptian flag, and the other, "Abbas Hilmi, Khedive, Egypt"; a fringed silk "God Save the King" scarf; and an 8"x5" flannel Turkey-Egypt flag. The other 7 items include a United Arab Republic postage first day of issue cover from 1958, a bond certificate of the Land Bank of Egypt dated April 17, 1905, and a card game titled Egyptian Trivia.
  - The Mameluke; or the Sign of the Mystic Tie, by B. Perley Poore, 1852 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - A Day with Royalty, B.C. 475, published 1901. Includes book dealer description. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Egyptian Trivia cards by Cassandra Vivian, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Bronze commemorative medal, featuring Mariette, Boulogne Sur Mer 1821, Boulaq 1881, Fondation de Musee de Boulaq, et du service des Antiquities Egyptiennes (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Sono Cairo 45 rpm records (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Maps and Plans accompanying Egypt Through the Stereoscope, 1902 (2 copies) (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - The Mentor: Capetown to Cairo, Nov. 1922 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - L'Egyptienne, Revue Mensuelle, Politique - Feminisme - Sociologie - Art, Oct - Nov, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - The Egyptian Red Book, and The Irish Green Book, published by William Blackwood and Sons, 1880s (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Land Bank of Egypt, dividend coupons, 1905 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - The Story of Some Old Friends, by George Pangalo (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Shrines of Bethlehem souvenir (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Flannel flag of Turkey Egypt (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - English / Arabic phrases and vocabulary (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Notes Sur Un Texte Copte du XIIIe Siecle, par M. P. Casanova (unbound / uncut sigantures) (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Bab-Zuweyla color lithograph, 1903 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Egyptian flag and crest printed on silk, in New York (2) (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Postal envelope from United Arab Republic featuring 50th Death Anniversary of Qasim Amin 1865-1908 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Decius Repetita Placebit, published by Arlington Chemical Company, Yonkers, N.Y. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Hand colored map of Cairo, A. H. Dufour, 1859 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Engraved printed map of Cairo, Harper's Hand Book (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Engraved map of Cairo, A. F. Dufour, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Color lithographs of Cairo Street, 1893 Chicago Exposition (2) (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Series VI: Maps and oversize printed and photographic material, 1895-1929
  There are 3 maps: an 1859 hand colored city map of Cairo; an 8-1/2"x11" black and white annotated map of Cairo; and a 7"x9" black and white annotated map of Cairo and the pyramids of Gizeh. 12 items are included among the oversize printed and photographic materials: 3 are color lithographs of Egyptian scenes. There are a fifteen-page portfolio of black and white photographs from the 1893 World's Columbian Exposition and a black and white page from Scientific American Nov. 16, 1895, with photos of the Atlanta Exposition. Also from the 1893 Columbian Exposition is a page of black and white photos of costumed participants. There are 3 sepia photographs of Cairo buildings. There are 2 large black and white photos on photographic paper, one of Cairo and pyramids from the air, and the other of the Midway and Tower in Streets of Cairo. Finally is the Oct. 1929 issue of Travel with the cover design titled "In Old Cairo."
  - English and Egyptian fringed white silk textile souvenir of Egypt (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Photos (landscapes and street scenes) (5) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Publications: Travel, October 1929; Scientific American, Nov. 16, 1895; Le Petit Journal, Supplement Illustre, July 15, 1900; World's Fair Educational Art Series, Vol. 1 No. 11, Jan. 18, 1894 "The Dream City" (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Unidentified book, possibly "Journal des Tribunaux Mixtes" (Box 6, Folder -)